<content>

	<alphabet name="A">	
		<heading name="Absolute duties"><![CDATA[Certain duties under health and safety law are of an absolute or strict nature.<br /><br />These duties are qualified by the terms ‘shall’ or ‘must’.<br /><br />For instance, under The Workplace (Health, Safety and Welfare) Regulations 1992 a workplace and the equipment, devices and systems shall be maintained in an efficient state, in efficient working order and in good repair.<br /><br />This means employers must comply with requirements regardless of cost, time or effort required.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Absorption"><![CDATA[The route of entry of hazardous substances through the skin.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Accident"><![CDATA[The term ‘accident’ can be defined in a number of ways:<br /><li>an unforeseeable event, often resulting in injury;</li><li>an unplanned and uncontrolled event, which has led to or could have caused injury to persons, damage to plant or other loss; and</li><li>a deviation from the normal, the expected or the planned, usually resulting in injury.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Accident statistics"><![CDATA[Accident statistics, as a reactive form of safety monitoring, generally take the form of an incident rate.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Active monitoring"><![CDATA[This form of monitoring entails the carrying out of a range of proactive safety monitoring exercises directed at preventing accidents, such as safety audits and safety inspections.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Act of parliament (STATUTE)"><![CDATA[This is the principal form of legislation that has gone through the parliamentary process to become statute, e.g. the Health and Safety at Work etc. Act 1974 (HSWA).<br /><br />The HSWA enables the Secretary of State for Employment to make regulations on a range of health and safety related matters, e.g. The Noise at Work Regulations 1989.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Adjustable guard"><![CDATA[A guard incorporating an adjustable element, which, once adjusted, remains in that position during a particular operation.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Alternative means of escape"><![CDATA[This is a second route, usually in the opposite direction to the first means of escape in the case of a fire, which may join the first means of escape.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Approved Code Of Practice (ACOP)"><![CDATA[The Health and Safety Commission (HSC) is empowered under the HSWA to approve and issue codes of practice for the purpose of supplementing information contained in statute and regulations.<br /><br />A code of practice can be drawn up by the HSC or some other body.<br /><br />In every case, however, any relevant government department or other body must be consulted beforehand and the approval of the Secretary of State for Employment must be obtained.<br /><br />Failure to comply with an ACOP can raise the presumption that the offender was in breach of the legislation unless ‘works of an equivalent nature’ are undertaken, which satisfy the requirements of the ACOP.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Arm protection"><![CDATA[This PPE may take the form of gauntlets, chain mail and leather arm protectors.<br /><br />This form of protection is commonly used where operators are using knives or other implements where there is a risk of arm injury.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Article for use at work"><![CDATA[This means:<br /><li>any plant designed for use or operation (whether exclusively or not) by persons at work, or persons who erect or install any fairground equipment; and</li><li>any article designed for use as a component in any such plant or equipment (the Health and Safety at Work etc. Act 1974).</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Attitude"><![CDATA[Variously defined as:<br /><li>a predetermined set of responses built up as a result of experience of situations; and</li><li>a tendency to respond favourably or unfavourably to certain persons, objects or situations.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Automatic guard"><![CDATA[A guard that is associated with, and dependent upon, the mechanism of the machinery and operates so as to remove physically from the danger area any part of a person exposed to the danger.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="B">		
		<heading name="Body protection"><![CDATA[This form of protection may include one-piece and two-piece overalls, donkey jackets, aprons, warehouse coats, foul-weather clothing, and clothing to protect against machinery, together with high-visibility clothing, life-jackets and buoyancy aids.<br /><br />Certain forms of body protection can be of the washable, semi-disposable or disposable type, such as overalls.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Breach of statutory duty"><![CDATA[In certain situations a breach of a criminal duty may give rise to civil liability.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Breathing apparatus"><![CDATA[This is generally taken to mean apparatus that replaces the surrounding air supply and provides the user with sufficient air to breathe normally.<br /><br />The use of breathing apparatus may be necessary in atmospheres contaminated with smoke and other airborne pollutants.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="C">		
		<heading name="Carbon dioxide extinguisher"><![CDATA[This extinguisher consists of a pressure cylinder filled with liquid carbon dioxide.<br /><br /.On operation of the trigger the liquid is discharged through the horn under its own pressure, being converted to carbon dioxide snow prior to application.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Carcinogen"><![CDATA[A cancer-causing substance.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Civil liability"><![CDATA[This refers to the ‘penalty’ that can be imposed by a civil court, e.g. county court, high court.<br /><br />A civil action generally involves individuals, with a plaintiff suing a defendant for a remedy or remedies. In most cases, the remedy takes the form of damages, a form of financial compensation.<br /><br />Civil actions commonly include allegations of negligence and/or breach of statutory duty.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Comfort ventilation"><![CDATA[This is the process of providing sufficient air for people to breathe and, to some extent, regulating temperature.<br /><br />It is directly related to the number of air changes per hour in a workplace according to the external ambient air temperature and the actual rate of air movement.<br /><br />Rates of air change will, in most cases, vary from summer to winter to maintain comfort ventilation.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Competent persons"><![CDATA[The appointment by an employer of suitable competent persons to undertake a range of examinations, inspections, operations and supervisory duties is well recognised in health and safety law.<br /><br />Generally, a competent person should have the appropriate skill, knowledge and experience to deal with the particular circumstances and be appointed by the employer.<br /><br />Under the MHSWR 1999, an employer must:<br /><li>appoint one or more competent persons to assist him in undertaking the measures he needs to take to comply with the requirements and prohibitions imposed by or under the relevant statutory provisions; and</li><li>appoint competent persons to oversee the emergency evacuation procedures.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="‘Corrosive’ classification"><![CDATA[Substances and preparations that may, on contact with living tissue, destroy them.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Criminal liability"><![CDATA[A crime is an offence against the state.<br /><br />Criminal liability refers to the responsibilities of persons under statutes and regulations and the penalties that can be imposed by the criminal courts, e.g. magistrates’ court and Crown court.<br /><br />The burden of proving a criminal charge ‘beyond reasonable doubt’ rests with the prosecution.<br /><br />Where a person is found guilty, a court will impose some form of punishment, namely, a fine and/or imprisonment.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="D">		
		<heading name="Danger"><![CDATA[Liability or exposure to harm; a thing that causes peril.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Dangerous occurrence"><![CDATA[An event listed in Schedule 2 of The Reporting of injuries, Diseases and Dangerous Occurrences Regulations 1995 (RIDDOR).<br /><br />Such events must be notified immediately, (see Chapter 2 for details on how to report).<br /><br />Examples of dangerous occurrences are the collapse or overturning of lifting machinery, unintentional explosions, gassing accidents and boiler explosions.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Deadstop device"><![CDATA[A form of safety trip device, incorporating a trip bar or arm, an electrical switch and brake, located in close proximity to a danger point on a machine.<br /><br />When the trip arm, e.g. a telescopic arm to a vertical drill, is touched, the machine motor automatically cuts out.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Disability glare"><![CDATA[The visually disabling effect produced by bright bare lamps directly in the line of sight (dazzle).]]></heading>
		<heading name="Discomfort glare"><![CDATA[A form of glare caused by too much contrast of brightness between an object and its background.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Display Screen Equipment"><![CDATA[Any alphanumeric or graphic display screen, regardless of the display process involved. (The Health and Safety (Display Screen Equipment) Regulations 1992.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Distance guard"><![CDATA[A guard that does not completely enclose a danger point or area but that places it out of normal reach.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Dry powder chemical extinguisher"><![CDATA[These appliances are of two types, stored pressure and gas cartridge. In both cases, the cylinder is fed with dry powder.<br /><br />In the stored pressure type, the cylinder is pressurised with dry air or nitrogen, and the operation of the trigger allows the pressure to expel the dry powder through the hose.<br /><br />With the gas cartridge type, the seal on the cartridge is broken by a plunger and the flow of powder is controlled by a trigger valve on the hose.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="E">
		<heading name="Ear protection"><![CDATA[Ear or hearing protection is designed to protect people from the risk of noise-induced hearing loss (occupational deafness).<br /><br />It takes three principal forms:<br /><li>ear plugs: fitted into the auditory canal;</li><li>ear defenders, muffs and pads: cover the whole ear and can reduce exposure by up to 50 dBA at certain frequencies; and</li><li>ear valves: inserted into the auditory canal, allowing normal conversation</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Emergency lighting"><![CDATA[This is provided to ensure safety when a normal lighting installation fails, and may take the form of standby lighting or escape lighting.<br /><br />Standby lighting enables essential work to continue, the level of illuminance depending upon the nature of the work.<br /><br />This may be between 5 and 100% of the illuminance provided by the normal installation.<br /><br />Escape lighting enables a building to be evacuated safely and may take the form of battery or generator-powered installations.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Employees’ duties"><![CDATA[<b>Under the HSWA 1974, employees must:</b><br /><li>take reasonable care for the safety of themselves and other persons who may be affected by their acts or omissions whilst at work;</li><li>cooperate with their employer so far as is necessary for him to comply with any duty or requirement under any of the relevant statutory provisions; and</li><li>not intentionally or recklessly interfere with or misuse anything provided for the purposes of health and safety at work in furtherance of a statutory requirement.</li><br /><br /><b>Under the MHSWR 1999, employees must:</b><br /><li>use any machinery, equipment, dangerous substance, transport equipment, means of production or safety device provided to him by his employer in accordance with any training received by him in the use of the equipment concerned and the instructions regarding that use that have been provided to him by his employer in compliance with the requirements and prohibitions imposed upon that employer by or under the relevant statutory provisions; and</li><li>inform their employer or any other employee with specific responsibility for the health and safety of his fellow employees:</li><li>of any work situation that represents a serious and immediate danger to health and safety; and</li><li>of any matter that represents a shortcoming in the employer’s protection arrangements for health and safety.</li><br /><br /><b>Under the HSWA 1974 it is the duty of every employer, so far as is reasonably practicable, to ensure the health, safety and welfare at work of all his employees. More particularly, this includes:</b><br /><li>the provision and maintenance of plant and systems of work that are, so far as is reasonably practicable, safe and without risks to health;</li><li>arrangements for ensuring, so far as is reasonably practicable, safety and absence of health risks in connection with the use, handling, storage and transport of articles and substances;</li><li>the provision of such information, instruction, training and supervision as is necessary to ensure, so far as is reasonably practicable, the health and safety of all employees;</li><li>so far as is reasonably practicable as regards any place of work under the employer’s control, the maintenance of it in a condition that is safe and without health risks, and the provision and maintenance of means of access to and egress from it that are safe and without health risks;</li><li>the provision and maintenance of a working environment for their employees that is, so far as is reasonably practicable, safe, without risk to health and adequate as regards facilities and arrangements for their welfare at work;</li><li>employers must prepare and, as often as is necessary, revise a written Statement of Health and Safety Policy, and bring the Statement and any revision of it to the notice of all their employees; and</li><li>every employer must consult appointed safety representatives with a view to making and maintaining arrangements that will enable them and their employees to cooperate effectively in promoting and developing measures to ensure the health and safety at work of the employees, and in checking the effectiveness of such measures.</li><br /><br /><b>Under the MHSWR 1999 every employer must:</b><br /><li>make a suitable and sufficient assessment of the risks to his own employees and other persons affected by his activities in order to identify the measures he needs to take to comply with the requirements and prohibitions imposed on him by or under the relevant statutory provisions;</li><li>review and revise risk assessments and implement changes where necessary;</li><li>ensure the effective planning, organisation, control, monitoring and review of the preventive and protective measures arising from the risk assessment;</li><li>provide health surveillance where necessary;</li><li>appoint one or more competent persons to assist him in complying with his duties under the relevant statutory provisions;</li><li>establish and, where necessary, give effect to procedures to be followed in the event of serious or imminent danger, and nominate competent persons to implement these procedures;</li><li>provide employers with comprehensible and relevant information on specific aspects;</li><li>where a workplace is shared, cooperate with other employers, take all reasonable steps to coordinate safety procedures, and inform other employers of the risks arising out of or in connection with his own undertaking;</li><li>provide comprehensible information to employees from an outside undertaking on the risks and measures he has taken to comply with the relevant statutory provisions;</li><li>take into account health and safety capabilities when allocating tasks;</li><li>ensure health and safety training of employees:</li><li>on recruitment; and</li><li>on being exposed to new or increased risks due to transfer, change of responsibility, introduction of new work equipment, change in existing work equipment, introduction of new technology, introduction of a new system of work or change of an existing system;</li><li>provide temporary workers with certain comprehensible information; and</li><li>consult with safety representatives in specified circumstances.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Employer’s liability"><![CDATA[Under the Employer’s Liability (Compulsory Insurance) Act 1969 employers are required to carry insurance against common law liability to their employees resulting in injury, disease and/or death. Failure to do so is a criminal offence.<br /><br />The policy must state that any person under a contract of service or apprenticeship who sustains injury, disease or death caused during the period of insurance and arising out of the course of employment will be covered for any legal liability on the part of the employer to pay compensation.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Enforcing authority"><![CDATA[The enforcing authorities are:<br /><li>the Health and Safety Executive (HSE);</li><li>local authorities; and</li><li>fire authorities for certain delegated matters.</li><br />Enforcement of health and safety legislation is undertaken by inspectors appointed under Section 20 of the HSWA and authorised by written warrant from the enforcing authority.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Escape lighting"><![CDATA[(See Emergency lighting.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Evacuation"><![CDATA[The process of moving people from a building or area to an identified assembly point.]]></heading>
		<heading name="‘Explosive’ classification"><![CDATA[Solid, liquid, pasty or gelatinous substances and preparations that may react exothermically without atmospheric oxygen, thereby quickly evolving gases and that, under defined test conditions, detonate, quickly deflagrate or, upon heating, quickly explode when partially confined.]]></heading>
		<heading name="‘Extremely flammable’ classification"><![CDATA[Liquid substances and preparations having an extremely low flashpoint and a low boiling point and gaseous substances and preparations that are flammable in contact with air at ambient temperature and pressure.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Eye protection"><![CDATA[Eye protection is designed to prevent injury arising from flying particles, dust, fumes, welding glare and splashes of hazardous substances, such as acids.<br /><br />Eye protection may take a number of forms:<br /><li>safety spectacles: with toughened glass or plastic lenses with plastic or metal frames and, in some cases, incorporating side shields;</li><li>safety goggles: which incorporate a cup surrounding each eye; and</li><li>eye and face shields: which can be hand-held, fixed to a helmet or strapped to the head.</li>]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="F">		
		<heading name="Face masks"><![CDATA[These generally incorporate a metal frame for holding a filtering medium against the nose and mouth to protect against inhalation of coarse dust particles or non-toxic paint sprays only.<br /><br />They afford no protection against gases, fumes, mists and other forms of airborne contamination.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Face shields"><![CDATA[These provide protection to the eyes and face and can be hand-held, fixed to a helmet or strapped to the head.<br /><br />They are manufactured in toughened polycarbonate materials.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Fire"><![CDATA[‘Fire’ can be defined in several ways:<br /><li>a spectacular example of a fast chemical reaction between a combustible substance and oxygen accompanied by the evolution of heat;</li><li>a mixture in gaseous form of a combustible substance and oxygen with sufficient energy put into the mixture to start a fire; and</li><li>an unexpected combustion generating sufficient heat or smoke resulting in loss of life, damage to plant, equipment, goods and buildings.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Fire alarm"><![CDATA[The most effective fire alarm is the human voice.<br /><br />Fire alarm systems can range from a simple hand bell to electronically actuated systems.<br /><br />Systems are commonly linked with heat and/or smoke detection systems, the detection system actuating the audible alarm and sprinkler systems.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Fire drill"><![CDATA[A planned or unplanned evacuation of a building or area in order to train and familiarise occupants with the means of escape.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Fire escape"><![CDATA[A commonly used term to indicate the structural means of escape from a building, such as an external metal staircase or fire-protected internal staircase.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Fire exit"><![CDATA[A designated door giving direct access to the open air and forming part of a means of escape in the event of fire.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Fire extinguishers"><![CDATA[These are appliances designed to be carried and operated by hand.<br /><br />They contain an extinguishing medium that can be expelled by the action of internal pressure and directed at a fire.<br /><br />The pressure may be stored or obtained through a chemical reaction or by the release of gas from a cartridge.<br /><br />All portable extinguishers must be coloured red and display a distinguishing label thus:<br /><li>Water....Red</li><li>Foam....Cream</li><li>Carbon dioxide....Black</li><li>Dry chemical powder....Blue</li><li>Wet chemical....Yellow</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Fire instructions"><![CDATA[A fire instruction is a notice informing people of the action they should take on either hearing a fire alarm or discovering a fire.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Fire triangle"><![CDATA[There are three requirements for the propagation of a fire, commonly known as the ‘fire triangle’, namely:<br /><li>Oxygen or air;</li><li>A fuel or combustible substance; and</li><li>A source of energy, heat or ignition.</li><br />The removal of one of the three elements of the fire triangle results in combustion failing to take place.]]></heading>
		<heading name="First Aid"><![CDATA[The skilled application of accepted principles of treatment on the occurrence of an accident or in the case of sudden illness, using facilities and materials available at the time.<br /><br />First aid is defined by law as follows:<br /><li>in cases where a person will need help from a medical practitioner or nurse, treatment for the purpose of preserving life and minimising the consequences of injury or illness until such help is obtained; and</li><li>treatment of minor injuries that would otherwise receive no treatment or that do not need treatment by a medical practitioner or nurse.</li><br />(The Health and Safety (First Aid) Regulations 1981.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Fixed guard"><![CDATA[A guard that has no moving parts associated with it, or dependent upon the mechanism of any machinery and that, when in position prevents access to a danger point or area.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Foam extinguishers"><![CDATA[These extinguishers take the form of chemical foam and stored pressure foam extinguishers.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Foot protection"><![CDATA[Foot protection includes safety boots, shoes, clogs, foundry boots, wellington boots, anti-static footwear and ankle protection.<br /><br />Foot protection should be waterproof, resistant to acids, alkalis, oils and other substances.<br /><br />It should incorporate steel toecaps where there is a risk of foot injury.<br /><br />With wet processes, wellington boots, incorporating a steel toecap, should be provided.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="G">
		<heading name="Gas safe register™"><![CDATA[By law all gas engineers must be on the Gas Safe Register™ to carry out gas work in Great Britain and the Isle of Man. The register can be checked at: www.gassaferegister.co.uk]]></heading>
		<heading name="Generic (MODEL) Risk Assessment"><![CDATA[A risk assessment produced once only for an identified type of activity, workplace or work group.<br /><br />For generic risk assessments to be effective:<br /><li>‘worst case’ situations must be considered; and</li><li>provision must be made in the assessment document to monitor the implementation of the controls that are or are not relevant in the case of a particular activity, workplace or work group.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Glare"><![CDATA[The effect of light that causes discomfort or impaired vision, which is experienced when parts of the visual field are excessively bright compared with the general surroundings.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Guard"><![CDATA[A physical barrier to protect persons from danger.<br /><br />(See Fixed guard, Adjustable guard, Distance guard, Interlocking guard and Automatic guard.)]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="H">		
		<heading name="Hand protection"><![CDATA[This includes gloves and gauntlets, principally concerned with protecting the hands from injuries such as cuts, abrasions and burns and those arising during manual handling operations and in extremes of temperature.]]></heading>
		<heading name="‘Harmful’ classification"><![CDATA[Substances and preparations that may cause death or acute or chronic damage to health when inhaled, swallowed or absorbed via the skin.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Hazard"><![CDATA[Something with the potential to cause harm.<br /><br />This can include substances or machines, methods of work and other aspects of work organisation.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Head protection"><![CDATA[This form of protection includes:<br /><li>safety helmets to protect the head from falling objects and overhead hazards;</li><li>industrial scalp protectors (bump caps) to protect against striking fixed obstacles, scalping or entanglement; and</li><li>caps and hairnets to prevent the hair from coming into contact with moving machinery.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Health"><![CDATA[A state of complete physical, mental and social well-being and not merely the absence of disease or infirmity.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Health and Safety at Work etc. Act 1974"><![CDATA[The HSWA covers all people at work except domestic workers in private employment and extends to the prevention of risks to the health and safety of the general public.<br /><br />The general objectives of the HSWA are:<br /><li>to secure the health, safety and welfare of all persons at work;</li><li>to protect others from the risks arising from workplace activities;</li><li>to control the obtaining, keeping and use of explosive or highly flammable substances; and</li><li>to control emissions into the atmosphere of noxious or offensive substances.</li><br />All duties are qualified by the term ‘so far as is reasonably practicable.’<br /><br />(See Employees’ duties, Employer’s duties, Reasonably practicable.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Health and Safety Executive"><![CDATA[This is the national health and safety enforcing authority.<br /><br />HSE inspectors have wide-ranging powers, including the power to serve Improvement Notices and Prohibition Notices.<br /><br />(See Improvement notice, Power of inspectors, Prohibition notice.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Hernia"><![CDATA[A protrusion of an organ from one compartment of the body into another, e.g. a loop of intestine into the groin or through the frontal abdominal wall.<br /><br />Both these forms of hernia can result from incorrect manual handling techniques and particularly from the adoption of bent back stances, which produce compression of the abdomen and lower intestines.]]></heading>
		<heading name="‘Highly flammable’ classification"><![CDATA[The following substances and preparations, namely:<br /><li>substances and preparations that may become hot and finally catch fire in contact with ambient temperature without any application of energy;</li><li>solid substances and preparations that may readily catch fire after brief contact with a source of ignition and that continue to burn or to be consumed after removal of the source of ignition;</li><li>liquid substances and preparations that have a very low flashpoint; and</li><li>substances and preparations that, in contact with water or damp air, evolve highly flammable gases in dangerous quantities.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Hoists and lifts"><![CDATA[General requirements for hoists and lifts are incorporated in the Lifting Operations and Lifting Equipment Regulations (LOLER) 1998.<br /><br />Every hoist or lift shall be:<br /><li>of good mechanical construction, sound material, adequate strength and properly maintained;</li><li>examined by a competent person every six months at least, recorded and, where defects are found, a report must be sent to the HSE;</li><li>every hoistway or liftway shall be efficiently protected by a substantial enclosure fitted with gates of such design and layout as to prevent, when the gates are shut, any person falling down the way or coming into contact with any moving part of the equipment. Any such gate must be fitted with an efficient interlocking device;</li><li>every hoist or lift and every enclosure shall be so constructed as to prevent any part of any person or any goods carried from being trapped between any part of the hoist or lift and any fixed structure or between the counterbalance weight or any other moving part; and</li><li>the safe working load of the hoist or lift must be conspicuously marked and must not be exceeded.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="HSE guidance notes"><![CDATA[The HSE issues Guidance Notes that have no legal status and are purely of an advisory nature, sometimes to supplement information in an ACOP.<br /><br />HSE Guidance Notes are issued in six specific series:<br /><li>General Safety (GS);</li><li>Chemical Safety (CS);</li><li>Environmental Hygiene (EH);</li><li>Medical Series (MS);</li><li>Plant and Machinery (PM); and</li><li>Health and Safety Guidance (HS(G)).</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Human error"><![CDATA[Limitations in human capacity to perceive, attend to, remember, process and act on information are all relevant in the context of human error.<br /><br />Typically, human error is associated with:<br /><li>lack of knowledge;</li><li>lack of concentration;</li><li>incapability; and</li><li>wilfulness.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Human factors"><![CDATA[This term is used to cover a range of issues, including:<br /><li>the perceptual, physical and mental capabilities of people and the interaction of individuals with their job and working environments;</li><li>the influence of equipment and system design on human performance; and</li><li>the organisational characteristics that influence safety-related behaviour.</li>These issues are affected by:<br /><li>the system for communication within the organisation; and</li><li>the training systems and procedures in operation, all of which are directed at preventing human error.</li>]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="I">
		<heading name="Ignition"><![CDATA[Ignition of a substance is brought about by the introduction of energy sufficient to raise a volume of the substance to its ignition temperature.<br /><br />Ignition sources include open flames, electrical equipment, friction, matches, lighters, static electricity, lightning, welding and other hot work, engines and spontaneous ignition of certain flammable substances.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Improvement notice"><![CDATA[An Improvement Notice is served on an employer and other persons when, in the opinion of an enforcement officer, a person, business or undertaking is not complying with the relevant statutory provisions and where action is required by a certain date.<br /><br />There is a right of appeal to an industrial tribunal against the notice, which suspends
its enforcement until a decision is reached by the tribunal.]]></heading>
	 	<heading name="Incident"><![CDATA[An event that does not result in injury, damage or loss but that may cause interruption of the work process.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Ingestion"><![CDATA[The taking into the body of substances through the mouth.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Inhalation"><![CDATA[The principal route of entry of hazardous substances, such as gases, dusts and vapours, into the body via the nose, mouth and respiratory tract.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Injection"><![CDATA[A forceful breach of the skin, perhaps as a result of injury, which can transmit hazardous substances past the skin barrier.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Injury"><![CDATA[Damage to the body, commonly as a result of an accident.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Interlocking guard"><![CDATA[A guard that has a moveable part so connected with the machinery controls that:<br /><li>the part(s) of the machinery causing danger cannot be set in motion until the guard is closed;</li><li>the power is switched off and the motion braked before the guard can be opened sufficiently to allow access to the dangerous parts; and</li><li>access to the danger point or area is denied while the danger exists.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="‘Irritant’ classification"><![CDATA[Non-corrosive substances and preparations that through immediate, prolonged or repeated contact with the skin or mucous membrane may cause inflammation.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
		
	<alphabet name="J">
		<heading name="Job safety analysis"><![CDATA[A technique that identifies all the accident prevention measures appropriate to a particular job or area of work activity, and the behavioural factors that most significantly influence whether or not these measures are taken.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="K">
	</alphabet>

	<alphabet name="L">	
		<heading name="Low voltage"><![CDATA[This is a protective measure against electric shock; the most commonly used reduced low voltage system is the 110 volt centre point earthed system.<br /><br />With this system the secondary winding of the transformer providing the 110 volt supply is centre tapped to earth, thus ensuring that at no part of the 110 volt circuit can the voltage to earth exceed 55 volts.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="M">	
		<heading name="Machine"><![CDATA[An apparatus for applying power, having fixed and moving parts, each with definite functions.]]></heading>	
		<heading name="Management"><![CDATA[The effective use of resources in the pursuit of organisational goals.<br /><br />‘Effective’implies achieving a balance between the risk of being in business and the cost of eliminating or reducing those risks.]]></heading>	
		<heading name="Mandatory signs"><![CDATA[Signs that indicate that a specific course of action is required, e.g. EYE PROTECTION MUST BE WORN.<br /><br />These signs are blue in colour, circular in shape, with a symbol or text in white.]]></heading>	
		<heading name="Manual handling operations"><![CDATA[This means any transporting or supporting of a load (including the lifting, putting down, pushing, pulling, carrying or moving thereof) by hand or by bodily force.<br /><br />(The Manual Handling Operations Regulations 1992.)]]></heading>	
		<heading name="Means of escape in case of fire"><![CDATA[A continuous route by way of a space, room, corridor, staircase, doorway or other means of passage, along or through which persons can travel from wherever they are in a building to the safety of the open air at ground level by their own unaided efforts.]]></heading>		
	</alphabet>
		
	<alphabet name="N">
		<heading name="Near miss"><![CDATA[An unplanned and unforeseeable event that could have resulted, but did not result, in human injury, property damage or other form of loss.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Negligence"><![CDATA[‘Negligence’ can be defined as ‘careless conduct injuring another’.<br /><br />It has been defined at common law as:<br /><li>the existence of a duty of care owed by the defendant to the plaintiff;</li><li>breach of that duty; and</li><li>injury, damage or loss resulting or caused by that breach.</li><br />All the above circumstances must be established by an injured employee before a civil claim for damages can be considered by a court.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Noise"><![CDATA[Noise is generally defined as ‘unwanted sound’.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Noiseinduced hearing loss (Occupational deafness)"><![CDATA[Exposure to noise may affect hearing in three ways:<br /><li>temporary threshold shift: a short-term effect, i.e. a temporary reduction in the ability to hear, which may follow exposure to excessive noise, such as that from firework explosions;</li><li>permanent threshold shift: a permanent effect where the limit of tolerance is exceeded in terms of the duration and level of exposure to noise and individual susceptibility; and</li><li>acoustic trauma: a condition that involves sudden damage to the ear from short-term intense exposure or even from one single exposure, e.g. gunfire, major explosions.</li>]]></heading>	
	</alphabet>

	<alphabet name="O">	
		<heading name="‘Oxidising’ classification"><![CDATA[Substances and preparations that give rise to an exothermic reaction in contact with other substances, particularly flammable substances.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="P">		
		<heading name="Permit to work"><![CDATA[A form of safe system of work operated where there is a high degree of foreseeable risk.<br /><br />A formal safety control system designed to prevent accidental injury to personnel, damage to plant, premises and product particularly when work with a foreseeably high hazard content is undertaken and the precautions required are numerous and complex.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Personal Protective Equipment (PPE)"><![CDATA[All equipment (including clothing affording protection against the weather) that is intended to be worn or held by a person at work and which protects him against one or more risks to his health and safety.<br /><br />Any addition or accessory designed to meet this objective.<br /><br />(The Personal Protective Equipment at Work Regulations 1992.)<br /><br />To interpret the markings on PPE go to www.hse.gov.uk and search for Standards for Personal Protective Equipment.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Postural fatigue"><![CDATA[A range of symptoms frequently experienced by users and operators of display screen equipment, in particular including lumbar, arm and shoulder pains, due to the adoption of unsuitable postures at a workstation.<br /><br />Generally, the more abnormal the posture, the greater the potential for postural fatigue and even long-term injury.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Powers of inspectors"><![CDATA[Inspectors have the following powers:<br /><li>to enter premises at any reasonable time accompanied, if necessary, by a police officer;</li><li>to take with them any duly authorised person, equipment or materials required;</li><li>to make examinations and investigations;</li><li>to direct that any premises, any part thereof or anything therein shall remain undisturbed for the purposes of examination and investigation;</li><li>to take measurements, photographs, recordings and samples;</li><li>to cause any article or substance to be dismantled or subjected to any process or test;</li><li>to take possession of any article or substance and detain for as long as is necessary;</li><li>to require any person to give information, answer questions and sign a declaration of truth;</li><li>to require production of, inspect and take copies of books and documents required to be maintained or otherwise;</li><li>to require any person to afford appropriate facilities and assistance;</li><li>to inform safety representatives of matters they have found following an investigation or examination;</li><li>to serve Improvement Notices and Prohibition Notices; and</li><li>to prosecute offenders.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Practicable duties"><![CDATA[A level of duty qualified by the term ‘so far as is practicable’ implies that the dutyholder must take all measures necessary ‘in the light of current knowledge or invention’ or ‘in the light of the current state of the art’ to comply with the duty.<br /><br />‘So far as is practicable’ implies a higher level of duty than ‘so far as is reasonably practicable’.<br /><br />Cost or sacrifice cannot be considered in this case.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Prohibition notice"><![CDATA[Served by enforcement officers where they are of the opinion that a work activity involves or will involve a risk of serious personal injury.<br /><br />The notice places a prohibition on specified activities until remedial measures are implemented.<br /><br />It is not necessary for a legal requirement to have been contravened, but that there is an immediate threat to life.<br /><br />A Prohibition Notice may be served with immediate effect or suspended for a period of time.<br /><br />An appeal to an industrial tribunal does not suspend the implementation of the requirements outlined in the notice.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Prosecution"><![CDATA[The bringing of a person before a court to answer a charge involving an alleged breach of the law.<br /><br />It is normal for the person charged to be served with a summons to attend court to answer to the charge or charges in question.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
		
	<alphabet name="Q">
	</alphabet>

	<alphabet name="R">
		<heading name="REACH"><![CDATA[<b>R</b>egistration, <b>E</b>valuation, <b>A</b>uthorisation and restriction of <b>Ch</b>emicals.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Reactive monitoring"><![CDATA[This includes a range of techniques, such as the investigation of accidents, ill-health and near misses, emergency and disaster planning, interpretation of statistical information and the implementation of a range of strategies to prevent recurrences of accidents and incidents.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Reasonably practicable"><![CDATA[A level of duty qualified by the term ‘so far as is reasonably practicable’ implies that a computation must be made by the employer or owner in which the quantum of risk is placed on one scale and the sacrifice involved in the measures necessary for averting the risk (whether in money, time or trouble) is placed in the other, and that, if it be shown that there is a gross disproportion between them, the defendants discharge the onus on them.<br /><br />(Edwards v National Coal Board (1949) 1 AER 743.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Reflected glare"><![CDATA[The reflection of bright light sources on shiny or wet work surfaces, such as glass or plated metal, which can almost entirely conceal the detail in or behind the object that is glinting.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Relevant statutory provisions"><![CDATA[The HSWA is an umbrella Act of general duties over, in some cases, former legislation, such as the Factories Act 1961 and the Offices, Shops and Railway Premises Act 1963.<br /><br />Both Acts and any regulations made under them are deemed to be the ‘relevant statutory provisions’ with regard to the HSWA.<br /><br />Schedule 1 of the HSWA lists regulations deemed to be the relevant statutory provisions.<br /><br />The Secretary of State for Employment may make regulations that are part of the relevant statutory provisions, e.g. the Control of Substances Hazardous to Health (COSHH) Regulations 2002.<br /><br />Regulations implementing various European Directives in the UK form part of the relevant statutory provisions, e.g. the MHSWR 1999.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Repetitive strain injury"><![CDATA[This covers well-known conditions such as tennis elbow, flexor tenosynovitis and carpal tunnel syndrome, and is usually caused or aggravated by work associated with repetitive and over-forceful movement, excessive workloads, inadequate rest periods and sustained or constrained postures.<br /><br />This results in pain or soreness due to inflammation of muscles and the synovial lining of the tendon sheath.<br /><br />Signs and symptoms include pain, tenderness, swelling and a grating sensation in the joint (crepitus) aggravated by pressure or movement.<br /><br />(See Work-related upper limb disorder.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Reportable disease"><![CDATA[A disease or condition affecting a person at work and listed in Schedule 3 to the RIDDOR - Reporting of Injuries, Diseases and Dangerous Occurrences Regulations 2013.<br /><br />On diagnosis by a registered medical practitioner, such a disease or condition must be reported.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Reportable injury"><![CDATA[Under the RIDDOR 2013 where any of the following events arise out of work activities it must be notified by the quickest practicable means and subsequently reported within 10/15 days to the Incident Contact Centre. (See Chapter 2 for further details on how to report.)<br /><br />These events are:<br /><li>the death of any person as a result of an accident, whether or not they are at work;</li><li>someone who is at work suffering a specified injury as a result of an accident;</li><li>someone who is not at work (e.g. a member of the public) suffering an injury as a result of an accident and is taken from the scene to a hospital for treatment, or if the accident happens at a hospital, suffering a specified injury;</li><li>someone at work is unable to do their normal work for more than seven days as a result of an injury caused by an accident at work;</li><li>the death of an employee, if this occurs some time after a reportable injury which led to the employee’s death, but not more than one year afterwards; and</li><li>a person at work suffering one of a number of specified diseases, provided that a doctor diagnoses the disease and the person’s job involves a specified work activity.</li><br />A specified injury is:<br /><li>a fracture, other than to fingers, thumbs and toes;</li><li>amputation of an arm, hand, finger, thumb, leg, foot or toe;</li><li>permanent loss of sight or reduction of sight;</li><li>crush injuries leading to internal organ damage;</li><li>serious burns (covering more than 10% of the body, or damaging the eyes, respiratory system or other vital organs);</li><li>scalpings (separation of skin from the head) which require hospital treatment;</li><li>unconsciousness caused by head injury or asphyxia; and</li><li>any other injury arising from working in an enclosed space, which leads to hypothermia, heat-induced illness or requires resuscitation or admittance to hospital for more than 24 hours.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Respirators"><![CDATA[Respirators are designed to protect the respiratory system of the wearer against harmful dusts, gases, fumes and other forms of airborne contamination.<br /><br />The correct selection of respiratory protection is vital, and management should decide on the respiratory protection required in individual circumstances on the basis of a formal risk assessment required under The Personal Protective Equipment Regulations 1992.<br /><br />Respirators may take the form of:<br /><li>general purpose dust respirators;</li><li>positive pressure powered dust respirators;</li><li>helmet-contained positive pressure respirators;</li><li>gas respirators:</li><li>cartridge type;</li><li>canister type; and</li><li>emergency escape respirators.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Risk"><![CDATA[Risk expresses the likelihood or probability that the harm from a particular hazard will be realised.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Risk assessment"><![CDATA[A risk assessment should usually involve identifying the hazards present in an undertaking (whether arising from work activities or from other factors, e.g. the layout of the premises) and then evaluating the risks involved, taking into account whatever precautions are being taken.<br /><br />A suitable and sufficient risk assessment:<br /><li>should identify the significant risks arising out of the work;</li><li>should enable the employer to identify and prioritise the measures that he needs to take to comply with the relevant statutory provisions; and</li><li>should be appropriate to the nature of the work and such that it remains valid for a reasonable period of time.</li><br />(ACOP, The Management of Health and Safety at Work Regulations 1999.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Risk rating"><![CDATA[A risk rating is used as part of the risk assessment process and, in most cases, is the numerical product of probability (likelihood) and the severity of the outcome in terms of injury, damage or loss. Probability and severity may be measured on a scale.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="S">		
		<heading name="Safe system of work"><![CDATA[The integration of people, machinery and equipment in a correct environment to provide the safest possible conditions in a work situation.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Safety"><![CDATA[The condition of being protected against physical, social, spiritual, financial, political, emotional, occupational, psychological, educational or other types of consequences of failure, damage, error, accident, harm or any other event which could be considered non-desirable.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Safety audit"><![CDATA[The systematic measurement by an organisation’s management of its health and safety programme against a series of specific standards.<br /><br />A safety audit subjects each area of an organisation’s activities to a systematic critical examination.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Safety culture"><![CDATA[The development of the right safety culture in an organisation is an important feature of the health and safety management process.<br /><br />This entails:<br /><li>acceptance of responsibility at and from the top, accompanied by the appropriate leadership and commitment;</li><li>conviction that high standards are achievable;</li><li>the setting and monitoring of relevant objectives/targets;</li><li>systematic identification and assessment of hazards, installation and regular review of protective measures;</li><li>immediate rectification of deficiencies;</li><li>promotion and reward of enthusiasm and good results;</li><li>acceptance that it is a long-term strategy that requires sustained effort and interest; and</li><li>ownership at all levels of the organisation.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Safety device"><![CDATA[A protective appliance, other than a guard, that eliminates or reduces danger before access to a danger point or area can be achieved.<br /><br />Safety devices can take the form of trip devices, pressure-sensitive mats, ultrasonic devices, two-hand control devices, overrun devices and mechanical restraint devices.<br /><br />(See Trip device, Two-hand control device, Deadstop device.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Safety inspection"><![CDATA[A safety inspection is generally taken to mean a scheduled inspection of a workplace or premises, to examine current levels of safety, working practices and compliance with the relevant statutory provisions and local systems at a particular time.<br /><br />Safety inspections can be undertaken by managers, health and safety specialists, safety representatives and enforcement officers.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Safety representative"><![CDATA[An employee appointed by his trade union to represent the members of that trade union in consultation with his employer on all matters affecting health and safety at work.<br /><br />Legal requirements relating to safety representatives and safety committees are covered in The Safety Representatives and Safety Committees Regulations 1977.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Safety sign"><![CDATA[</li><li>Prohibition signs – circular with a red band enclosing a crossed out symbol on a white background, such as ‘NO SMOKING’.</li><li>Warning signs – triangular in shape with a yellow background and black borders, symbols and text, such as ‘LPG – HIGHLY FLAMMABLE’.</li><li>Mandatory signs – circular in shape, incorporating a white mandatory symbol and/or text on a blue background, such as ‘WEAR EYE PROTECTION’.</li><li>Safe Condition signs – a green square or rectangle with symbols or lettering in white, such as ‘FIRE EXIT’.</li><br />Under the Health and Safety (Safety Signs and Signals) Regulations 1996 employers must use a safety sign wherever there is a risk to health and safety that cannot be avoided or properly controlled by other means.<br /><br />Signs must contain a pictogram instead of relying solely on text.<br /><br />Fire safety signs and signals are included and FIRE EXIT signs must incorporate the ‘Running Man’ pictogram.<br /><br />Pipework containing dangerous substances must be marked, by fixing labels or signs at sampling and discharge points, together with small stores containing dangerous substances.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Statement of health and safety policy"><![CDATA[There is a general duty under the HSWA for an employer to prepare and, as often as may be necessary, revise a written statement of his general policy with regard to health and safety at work of his employees and the organisation and arrangements for the time being in force for carrying out that policy, and to bring the statement and any revision of it to the notice of his employees.<br /><br />The principal features of a statement of health and safety policy are:<br /><li>a statement of intent;</li><li>the organisation, in terms of accountability and responsibility; and</li><li>the arrangements that detail the systems and procedures for monitoring performance and overall implementation of the objectives detailed in the statement of intent.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Stress"><![CDATA[Stress can be defined in a number of ways:<br /><li>the common response to attack (Selye, 1936);</li><li>a psychological response that follows failure to cope with problems;</li><li>a feeling of sustained anxiety that, over a period of time, leads to disease; and</li><li>the non-specific response of the body to any demands made upon it.</li>]]></heading>
		<heading name="Substance hazardous to health"><![CDATA[This means any substance (including any preparation) that is:<br /><li>listed in Part 1 of the approved supply list as dangerous for supply within the meaning of The Chemicals (Hazard Information and Packaging for Supply) 2009 (CHIP) Regulations and for which an indication of danger specified for the substance in Part V of that list is very toxic, toxic, harmful, corrosive or irritant;</li><li>specified in Schedule 1 of the COSHH regulations (which lists substances assigned maximum exposure limits) or for which the HSC has approved an occupational exposure standard;</li><li>a biological agent;</li><li>dust of any kind when present at a substantial concentration in air; and</li><li>not mentioned above, which creates a hazard to the health of any person that is comparable with the hazards created by substances the above-mentioned.</li><br />(The Control Of Substances Hazardous to Health Regulations 2002.)]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="T">
		<heading name="‘Toxic’ classification"><![CDATA[Substances and preparations that in low quantities can cause death or acute or chronic damage to health when inhaled, swallowed or absorbed via the skin.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Training"><![CDATA[The systematic development of attitude, knowledge and skill patterns required by an individual to perform adequately a given task.<br /><br />(Department of Employment and Productivity (1978) Glossary of Training Terms: HMSO London.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Training need"><![CDATA[A training need exists when the optimum solution to an organisation’s problem is through some form of training.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Trip device"><![CDATA[A means whereby any approach by a person beyond the safe limit of workingmachinery causes the device to actuate and stop the machinery or reverse its motion.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Two-hand control device"><![CDATA[A device that requires both hands to operate the machinery controls, thus CONTROL DEVICE affording a measure of protection from danger only to the machinery operator and not other persons.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
		
	<alphabet name="U">
		<heading name="Use (Display Screen Equipment)"><![CDATA[This means use for or in connection with work.<br /><br />(the Health and Safety (Display Screen Equipment) Regulations 1992.)]]></heading>
		<heading name="User (Display Screen Equipment)"><![CDATA[An employee who habitually uses display screen equipment as a significant part of his normal work.<br /><br />(the Health and Safety (Display Screen Equipment) Regulations 1992.)]]></heading>
	</alphabet>

	<alphabet name="V">
		 <heading name="Ventilation"><![CDATA[Ventilation implies the movement of air through a building. This may be by natural or mechanical means or by a combination of both.<br /><br />The principal features of a ventilation system are:<br /><li>the provision and maintenance of the circulation of fresh air in every occupied part of a workplace (comfort ventilation); and</li><li>the rendering harmless of all potentially injurious airborne contaminants, e.g. dusts, fumes, gases (exhaust ventilation).</li>]]></heading>
		 <heading name="‘Very toxic’ classification"><![CDATA[Substances and preparations that in very low quantities can cause death or acute or chronic damage to health when inhaled, swallowed or absorbed via the skin.]]></heading>
		 <heading name="Vibration"><![CDATA[The transmission of force from work processes into the worker.]]></heading>
		 <heading name="Visual fatigue"><![CDATA[Eyestrain and discomfort experienced by many people using display screen equipment, which may be due to a combination of both eyesight defects and poor workstation design.<br /><br />Vision screening of display screen equipment users should be undertaken on a regular basis and where users are experiencing the symptoms of visual fatigue.]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="W">
		<heading name="Warning signs"><![CDATA[(See Safety sign)]]></heading>
		<heading name="Watercontaining extinguisher"><![CDATA[There are several types of water-containing extinguisher.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Work equipment"><![CDATA[Under The Provision and Use of Work Equipment Regulations 1998 (PUWER), ‘work equipment’ is defined as including any machinery, appliance, apparatus or tool and any assembly of components that, in order to achieve a common end, are arranged and controlled so that they function as a whole.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Work-related ill health (occupational ill health)"><![CDATA[An illness or condition caused or made worse by the work carried out by an individual worker or sometimes by workers carrying out particular tasks.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Work-related upper limb disorder"><![CDATA[A group of conditions occasionally experienced by keyboard operators, formerly referred to as repetitive strain injury.<br /><br />These disorders affect the soft tissues of the hand, wrist, arm and shoulder.<br /><br />Typical symptoms include pain, restriction of joint movement and swelling of the soft tissues.]]></heading>
		<heading name="Workstation"><![CDATA[This means an assembly comprising:<br /><li>display screen equipment (whether provided with software determining theinterface between the equipment and its operator or user, a keyboard or anyother input device);</li><li>any optional accessories to the display screen equipment;</li><li>any disk drive, telephone, modem, printer, document holder, work chair, work desk, work surface or other item peripheral to the display screen equipment; and</li><li>the immediate environment around the display screen equipment.</li><br />(The Health and Safety (Display Screen Equipment) Regulations 1992.)]]></heading>
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="X">
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="Y">
	</alphabet>
	
	<alphabet name="Z">
	</alphabet>
	
</content>